<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE intro
  SYSTEM "../Symbols.dtd">
<intro xmlns="Unit"
       xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xsi:schemaLocation="Unit file:/C:/xampp/htdocs/moodle/mod/msm/NewSchemas/Unit.xsd">
   <block>
      <block.body>
         <para>
            <para.body>We use the term ‘analysis’ here as short for the mathematical subject of ‘mathematical analysis’. At the heart of this subject lie the concepts</para.body>
         </para>
         <ul>
		          <li>
               <para>
                  <para.body>infinite process</para.body>
               </para>
            </li>
		          <li>
               <para>
                  <para.body>convergence and limit</para.body>
               </para>
            </li>
		          <li>
               <para>
                  <para.body>failure of convergence</para.body>
               </para>
            </li>
	        </ul>
         <para>
            <para.body>Applied to functions between sets of real numbers, this leads to the concepts of continuity, derivative, integral.</para.body>
         </para>
         <para>
            <para.body>Historically, we find the earliest use of such limit methods in the work of the ancient Greeks. A famous example is Archimedes’ method of exhaustion to computing the area of a disk.
		
		Even earlier, Zeno describes scenarios each of which is based upon some infinite process. The process is manipulated in a skillfully incorrect way to arrive at a 
		<subordinate>
                  <hot>paradoxical conclusion</hot>
                  <companion>
                     <unit.ref unitId="Illustr_ZenoParadox"/>
                     <info>
				
				                    <para>
                           <para.body>See details of this paradox</para.body>
                        </para>
			                  </info>
                  </companion>
               </subordinate>.
	</para.body>
            <index.author>
               <name>
				              <first/>
				              <last>Archimedes of Syracuse</last>
			            </name>
               <info>
				              <para>
                     <para.body>Appears here for his approach to computing the area of a disk.</para.body>
                  </para>
			            </info>
            </index.author>
         </para>
         <para>
            <para.body>Systematic, yet informal and intuitive use of infinite process and their limits started in the second half of the 17th century, notably with the invention of differential and integral calculus: Newton, Leibniz. The early development of mathematical analysis was driven significantly by the desire to place such intuitive use of limits on a solid foundation: Cauchy, Weierstraß, etc. Now, apart from being a vast subject in its own right, mathematical analysis has branched of into generalizations: points set topology, measure theory, operator theory, ... which carry their own names.</para.body>
         </para>
         <para>
            <para.body>Here we treat .... (what this online text contains)</para.body>
         </para>
         <para>
            <para.body>The reader can consult 
		<subordinate>
                  <hot>background materials</hot>
                  <external.link href="../SetsNaive/Sets.xml" target="sets" type="xml"/>
               </subordinate>
		on the language of sets and basic principles of predicate logic as the need arises.</para.body>
         </para>
      </block.body>
   </block>
</intro>
