<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE unit
  SYSTEM "../Symbols.dtd">
<unit xmlns="Unit"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      unitid="Sec_Velocity"
      xsi:schemaLocation="Unit file:/C:/xampp/htdocs/moodle/mod/msm/NewSchemas/Unit.xsd">
   <titles>
      <title>Vectors Modeling Velocities</title>
      <plain.title>Velocities</plain.title>
   </titles>
   <intro>
      <block>
         <block.body>
            <para>
               <para.body>When a particle moves in space, it changes its location at each instant. This change of location is characterized by the direction and the speed of the motion at that instant. Both data combined comprise the velocity at that instant. As velocity is characterized by direction and magnitude, we may represent it by a 
			<subordinate>
                     <hot>vector</hot>
                     <info>
                        <info.caption>Illustration of Vectors representing Velocities</info.caption>
                        <para>
                           <para.body>For example, suppose a vector of length 1 corresponds to the speed of 20km/h. Then the following arrows represent velocities as indicated.</para.body>
                        </para>
                        <para align="center">
                           <para.body/>
                        </para>
                     </info>
                  </subordinate>. The direction of the vector gives the direction of the motion and the length of the vector corresponds to the speed.
		</para.body>
               <index.glossary>
                  <term>velocity</term>
                  <term>vector</term>
               </index.glossary>
               <index.glossary>
                  <term>vector</term>
                  <term>velocity</term>
               </index.glossary>
            </para>
         </block.body>
      </block>
   </intro>
   <body>
      <block>
         <block.body>
            <para>
               <para.body>Experiments show that superposition of motions corresponds to addition of the corresponding velocity vectors. For example: The motion of a person on a ship relative to a point on shore is superpositioned from</para.body>
            </para>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <para>
                     <para.body>The motion of the water relative to the point on shore</para.body>
                  </para>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <para>
                     <para.body>The motion of the ship relative to the water surrounding it</para.body>
                  </para>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <para>
                     <para.body>The motion of the person relative to the structure of the ship.</para.body>
                  </para>
               </li>
            </ul>
            <para>
               <para.body>The velocity vector of the moving person relative to a point on shore is the sum of these three velocity vectors.</para.body>
            </para>
            <para>
               <para.body>Similarly, the motion of an aircraft relative to the ground depends upon the wind which carries the aircraft and the superimposed motion resulting from the aircraft’s own propulsion.</para.body>
            </para>
            <para align="center">
               <para.body/>
            </para>
         </block.body>
      </block>
   </body>
   <studymaterials xmlns="">
      <exercise.pack.ref exercisePackID="Exe_ModelingVelocity"/>
   </studymaterials>
</unit>